My Wounds
My parents have been good to me.
They loved me very much.
And yet they didn't have a good
relationship as husband and wife.
Ever since I was a child,
I would try to cheer up my father.
My mother was an introvert and
didn't tell anyone of her marital issues.
So I would often end up keeping
her company as she would vent.
While I consoled them both
and thought good things of them,
I decided I won't get married myself.
Despite such thoughts,
I ended up marrying a man whom
my parents strongly disapproved of.
While I married against their will, I ironically
faced marital difficulties from day one.
My husband and I never had
arguments while we dated,
and yet from day one we fought
more than my parents ever did.
I tried to be responsible for the decision
I made against my parent's wishes.
Hence I didn't tell my
parents about my issues.
I lived on thinking as if I didn't exist.
But realizing I would have to live
the next 50 years this way,
I decided I should seek a new life
even if it meant hurting my parents.
Hence I got a divorce.
Last year, I joined
an enlightenment retreat.
For years after the divorce, I couldn't
overcome my hatred towards my husband.
when I joined an enlightenment retreat,
i would like to find a way to forgive him.
But during the retreat,
I truly realized I was the one with fault
for not having understood him.
Returning from retreat,
my mother opened up to me about
her unhappy marriage of 40 years.
She shared all the painful
words my father had said,
words that she kept to herself all along.
I empathized with her and
consoled her as I always did.
It's been 2 months since then. For some
reason I no longer want to see my parents.
I just don't want to invest
any emotions towards them.
As your teachings speak to me, I wanted
to ask you why I'm feeling this way.
It's fully understandable
for your mother to feel pain.
And yet her pain has now become your pain.
It's odd that you feel
this way after the retreat.
The real question is why you are hurt
by acknowledging your mother's pain.
(Questioner) Am I feeling this way
because I've been hurt?
Of course you are.
You no longer want to see your mother
and father because you've been hurt.
Her pain has now become yours.
Hearing your mother's painful stories,
the pain has transferred over to you.
As you've been hurt,
you don't want to face your father.
You don't want to face
your mother living that way
either as she has hurt you
through her stories.
It's neither your mother or
your father's story. It is now yours.
I didn't even realize
the fact that I've been hurt.
I only wondered
why I was feeling this way.
You are hurt, hence you are
captivated with thoughts.
In short, you are trapped
in your feelings of hatred.
It's like being engrossed with hatred towards
a sexual abuser after experiencing abuse.
It's as if you are engrossed with hatred
towards someone that stole money from you.
You are caught up in that one thought.
The same thing happened when you held
onto hatred towards your husband.
You are currently engrossed in a thought.
As soon as you acknowledge you are
obsessing over it, you can get over it.
With your husband, you were
able to acknowledge that
you weren't in a position to forgive.
You realized that you were insisting upon
a thought, and that you were caught up.
You realized he had his
own reasons and let go.
Hence you were able
to resolve your troubles.
Just as you've done, you should realize
that you are getting caught up on a thought.
Think to yourself, "Now I know that
mom was in pain for such reasons."
As you've only heard your
mother's side of the story,
you don't even know the whole truth.
And even if she's telling the whole truth,
it is only one of many things
happening in this world.
Let's say someone murdered a man.
If I experience pain from hearing of it,
it's my pain to bear
and not the other person's.
You are treading that line
and held up on it.
You are blaming your own problem on
your parents, hence unable to resolve it.
Your pain is your own problem.
We hear many stories throughout life.
We hear of fathers molesting daughters.
We hear of affairs with brother-in-laws.
We hear of sexual offenders
marrying their victims.
We hear of criminals raising
the kid of their murdered victims,
and kids finding out about it.
There are endless stories in this world.
We don't get hurt by these stories when they
are other people's stories and not our own.
We just say, "Whoa, what a tragic story."
Your story is about your own mother and
father, hence you are feeling the pain.
It has become your own pain.
You've become held up on it.
Listening to your mother's story,
you are trapped in that hindrance.
Feel free to ask questions if any.
Then how can I train myself to be able to
recognize such illusions in the moment?
We as humans easily
fall into a deluded state.
When feeling anger,
you should acknowledge that you are
caught up in thinking you are right.
You should think, 'Ah, I've yet again
obsessed over thinking I am right.'
Once you acknowledge it, it's the same
as getting up after having fallen.
We constantly fall
due to unconscious thoughts and
feelings we've built through the years.
They come to us
without us even knowing it.
Acknowledge the fact that you have fallen
and continue practicing getting up.
Children learn to ride a bike by going
through many trials and errors.
At a certain point, they start riding.
As you fall again and again and practice
acknowledging you have fallen,
you become aware that you're falling
as you fall. Then you get back up.
You were told your mother's story, and
you have fallen to a thought right now.
You've made an excuse
for yourself to fall.
You're telling yourself, "I've been told
a story I can't help but fall for."
It's like saying, "Staying out
till 10pm is ok, but 12am is not."
"I can forgive you for your drinking,
but I can't forgive affairs."
You're saying certain stories of your
mother are tolerable, while others aren't.
Notice that you are falling,
get up and continue to strive.
Tell yourself that even if you fall,
you won't spend more than a day down.
Reflect upon your day
before every morning,
and acknowledge what problems you are
entrapped with that are frustrating you.
In reality,
people spend a year, 10 years, 30 years
without acknowledging they have fallen.
They suddenly realize their fault of
30 years by attending a retreat.
Only then do they let go.
Once you experience this,
you should make an effort
not to be captivated for too long.
Once you're captivated, even
Buddha can't help save you from it.
Only you yourself can get out of it.
No matter how bright a day it is,
it's dark if you keep your eyes shut.
No matter how hard you pray and scream,
the world remains dark to you.
You must open your own eyes.
It's not important whether Buddha or God
is coming to this world or not.
The important thing is for you
to open your own eyes.
There's no use talking of others
unless you open your eyes yourself.
You are swayed by your mother's stories
and struggling to find
your way with eyes closed.
While doing so you're making
excuses for yourself.
Just as you've made excuses about
your husband, you are making excuses.
You are holding on to
the thought that the stories
of your parents are worth
despairing over.